<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true reformation of manners, or, The nature and qualifications of true zeal in a sermon preach'd in the parish church of Bridgewater : occasion'd by a more than ordinary concourse of dissenters there, upon that pretence / by Matth. Hole ...</title>
            <author>Hole, Matthew, 1639 or 40-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8060</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11803965</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11803965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44148)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 534:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true reformation of manners, or, The nature and qualifications of true zeal in a sermon preach'd in the parish church of Bridgewater : occasion'd by a more than ordinary concourse of dissenters there, upon that pretence / by Matth. Hole ...</title>
                  <author>Hole, Matthew, 1639 or 40-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield for Henry Clements,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Galatians IV, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Enthusiasm --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Enthusiasm --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49401:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>True Reformation of Manners,</hi> OR THE NATURE and QUALIFICATIONS OF True Zeal: IN A SERMON Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>BRIDGWATER:</hi> Occaſion'd by a more than ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Diſſenters there, upon that Pretence.</p>
            <p>By <hi>MATTH. HOLE,</hi> B. D. And Vicar of <hi>Stokegurſy</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 King. 10.16.</bibl> 
               <hi>Come with me, and ſee my Zeal for the Lord.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> for <hi>Henry Clements,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49401:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49401:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of the enſuing Diſcourſe, is not to hinder, but promote Reformation, by directing to the true way and means conducing thereunto: Neither is there any thing in it to Reproach, but only to Regulate our <hi>Zeal,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives all its Goodneſs from the Object, or End to which it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; and like Fire, is either uſeful or dangerous, according as it keeps, or leaves its due place and bounds.</p>
            <p>I know 'tis hard, and perhaps improper too, to treat coldly of this Subject, which is apt to excite a Warmth in the Speaker, and to enkindle alſo ſome Heat in the Hearers: And therefore 'twill require no ſmall Skill, to know the true limits and meaſures of this Vertue, and likewiſe no leſs Care to obſerve and keep within them.</p>
            <p>For private Perſons to be very ſolicitous about the amending their own Ways, and reforming their particular Errors and Vices, is a very commendable Property and Duty of a good Chriſtian: But for ſuch to be over-buſy and clamorous about the Reforming others, is many times to go out of their Station, and to meddle with things that appertain not to them. True Reformation, like Charity, begins at home, and makes Men more careful to correct their own Faults, than to pry into and cenſure the Manners of others: Such <hi>Cenſores morum</hi> had need have not only ſufficient Authority, but an exemplary and unſpotted Integrity; leſt their own Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages ſhould upbraid the forwardneſs of their <hi>Zeal,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute their goodlieſt Pretences.</p>
            <p>They that can allow themſelves in the hainous Sins of Schiſm, Diviſion and Diſobedience, may indeed talk and pretend much to Reformation, but can never be true Reformers: Such a prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Zeal</hi> hath commonly very bad Deſigns conceal'd under it; and
<pb facs="tcp:49401:3"/>'tis well known what direful Evils have been contrived and acted under this mask of Reformation: So that we are concern'd to watch our <hi>Zeal,</hi> as we do our Fire, leſt it grow headſtrong and exorbitant, and ſet not only whole Houſes, but whole Kingdoms in a Combuſtion; that we be not twice deceiv'd by the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice.</p>
            <p>I hope this warm Subject hath not tranſported me beyond the Bounds of Reaſon and Meekneſs in the handling of it; and that no wiſe Reader will ſee any juſt cauſe to complain of it, as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrical or Sarcaſtical.</p>
            <p>To rectify a miſtaken <hi>Zeal,</hi> and prevent the Danger of it, were the ſole Ends of Preaching this Sermon; and to anſwer the Requeſts of ſome, and remove the Prejudices of others, were the true Reaſons of its Publication.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>FAREWEL.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49401:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GALAT. IV. Part of the 18th Verſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>It is good to be Zealouſly affected always in a good thing.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE occaſion of theſe Words, was from ſome falſe Teachers, that had crept into the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> with a deſign to deſtroy the Credit of the Apoſtle, and the Doctrine deliver'd by him: To which end they preach'd up <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and other Rites and Ceremonies of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, on purpoſe to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Truths of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>In this Attempt they prevail'd ſo far, as to ſhake the Faith of many, who began to decry the Apoſtle, and to cry up thoſe deceitful Teachers above him. This put St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in this Chapter, upon reaſoning the Caſe with them, ver. 16. <hi>Am I become your Enemy becauſe I tell you the Truth? i. e.</hi> Am I become vile and deſpicable in thoſe <hi>eyes,</hi> which you would, not long ſince, have <hi>pluck'd out and given to me?</hi> How comes this change to be made in you, that the great Love
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49401:4"/>you lately bore to my Perſon and Doctrine, is thus of a ſudden turn'd into a Hatred of both? Why, he found that an <hi>Enemy</hi> had done this; <hi>i. e.</hi> Thoſe falſe Teachers, taking the opportunity of his Abſence, had planted their Tares, to hinder the growth of that good Seed he had ſow'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; and therefore with great earneſtneſs cautions theſe <hi>Galatians</hi> againſt them, as the great enemies of their Faith and Salvation; let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them know, that whatever ſhew they might make of <hi>Zeal</hi> towards GOD, or Affection towards them, there was nothing under it, but Falſhood and Hypocriſy. <hi>They Zealouſly affect you,</hi> ſaith he, ver. 17. <hi>but not well:</hi> There is no Sincerity in their goodlieſt Pretences, and in all they ſay or do, their Love is not to you, but themſelves; Yea, <hi>They would exclude you,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that you might affect them:</hi> meaning, that they would ſhut you out from the true Faith, that you might affect their Perſons, and embrace their Errors. Wherefore he wills them to beware of them, and to ſhun them as Cheats and Impoſtors; and from their falſe and counterfeit <hi>Zeal,</hi> takes occaſion to recommend True <hi>Zeal</hi> to them, in the Words of the Text: <hi>But it is good to be Zealouſly affected always in a good thing.</hi> In treating of which Words, I muſt enquire,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Into the Nature of <hi>Zeal,</hi> and ſhew what it is to be <hi>Zealouſly affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49401:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I muſt ſpeak to the two Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of true <hi>Zeal</hi> mention'd in the Text; the one reſpecting the Time of its continuance, which muſt be <hi>always;</hi> the other, the Object about which it is to be employ'd, which is a <hi>good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I muſt ſhew the Goodneſs or Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of true <hi>Zeal</hi> from thoſe Words, <hi>It is good to be Zealouſly affected,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I muſt lay open ſome of the Miſtakes and Miſcarriages of <hi>Zeal,</hi> and then conclude with an Inference or two from the whole.</p>
            <p>I begin then with the Enquiry into the Nature of <hi>Zeal,</hi> that we may ſee what it is to be Zealouſly affected; and here we may note,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>Zeal,</hi> in the general Notion of it, is <hi>a warmth of Mind, that carries it out in an eager purſuit of its Object, accompanied with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation at any thing that oppoſes, or lies in its way:</hi> And this is ſometimes in Scripture, and other Authors, taken in a bad fence, for Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Wrath, and bitter Envyings: St. <hi>James</hi> makes mention of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>bitter Zeal,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from an over-heated and exaſperated Mind, and is tranſlated, <hi>bitter Envyings,</hi> Jam. 3.14. St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is render'd, <hi>Emulations,</hi> among the works of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. This is an inordinate heat of the Soul, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by 'tis carried out too eagerly after ſome earthly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49401:5"/>ſenſual Objects or Deſigns. But paſſing by this, we are now to treat of a Religious <hi>Zeal,</hi> which is <hi>a warm and powerful Inclination of the Mind after Heaven and Heavenly things.</hi> For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding whereof, we muſt note,</p>
            <p>2ly, That <hi>Zeal</hi> is not any one ſingle Paſſion or Affection, but a mixture or compoſition of more; 'tis made up chiefly of Love and Anger, together with thoſe intermediate Paſſions, of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, Joy, Indignation, and the like, that partake of both. The firſt and great Ingredient of <hi>Zeal</hi> is Love, for none can be Zealouſly affected to any thing, which he doth not truly love; and where that is, 'twill draw after it a deſire of attaining and enjoying it; and according to the degrees of love will the deſire encreaſe, and improve into longings and impatience. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zeal</hi> is accompanied with Joy and Delight in pleaſing and poſſeſſing what it makes after, and where the Object is infinite, as when 'tis plac'd on GOD, it advances into Extaſy and Rapture. Furthermore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anger</hi> is an Ingredient of <hi>Zeal,</hi> which ſets the Soul againſt whatever oppoſes the thing Beloved; and proportionable to the oppoſition, does the Anger encreaſe, ariſing ſometimes to Wrath and Indignation, and upon any fruſtration 'tis at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with Grief and Sorrow.</p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>Zeal compounded</hi> of various and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49401:5"/>Paſſions, upon the well or ill <hi>tempering</hi> and <hi>mixing</hi> whereof, does the goodneſs or badneſs of <hi>Zeal</hi> depend. That <hi>Zeal</hi> that hath the greateſt mixture of the mild, loving and charitable Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections is commonly the beſt; that wherein the harſh, ſoure and hot Paſſions are moſt predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is very often inordinate: And that, where the angry Paſſions not only exceed, but exclude the more calm and benign Ones, is generally ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Moreover, <hi>Zeal</hi> is not only a compoſition of ſundry Paſſions, but a <hi>high degree</hi> and <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of them, and beſpeaks not barely the <hi>reality,</hi> but a <hi>fervency</hi> of Affection; 'tis ſuch a warmth of Mind, as influences the <hi>whole</hi> Man, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all the Powers of the Soul more <hi>vigorous</hi> and <hi>lively</hi> in its deſires and proſecutions; and ſo 'tis oppos'd to Coldneſs and Lukewarmneſs.</p>
            <p>So that true <hi>Zeal</hi> is a gracious conſtitution of the whole Mind, and is rather a <hi>conſtellation</hi> of Graces, than <hi>one particular</hi> Grace, 'tis what Health is to Life, the ſpring of all its activity and motion; and reſembles that Heroick Vertue deſcrib'd by the Moraliſts, which is not ſo much a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Vertue of its ſelf, as the <hi>higheſt pitch</hi> and <hi>eminence</hi> of all other Vertues.</p>
            <p>From this brief deſcription of <hi>Zeal</hi> we may learn, what it is to be <hi>Zealouſly affected;</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to have the Mind warmly ſtirring or moving in earneſt deſires, and an eager purſuit of ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49401:6"/>ſuitable and deſirable Object, and conſequently two things muſt concur to this zealous Affection, <hi>viz.</hi> Light in the head, and Heat in the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To be Zealouſly affected implies light and knowledge in the Head, for <hi>Ignoti nulla Cupido,</hi> None can affect that, of which he hath no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Light is the Director of <hi>Zeal,</hi> without which 'twill miſtake its Object, and neceſſarily go awry. 'Tis a <hi>blind</hi> Zeal, that is void of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and therefore what Light is to the Eye, that Knowledge is to the Soul, it ſhews its way, and guides all its operations. Again,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To be Zealouſly affected imports not only light in the Head, but heat in the Heart; and therefore 'tis often compar'd to Fire, whoſe property it is to warm and enliven, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles it <hi>a fervency of Spirit,</hi> Rom. 12.11. which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ſuch an inward warmth of Mind, as <hi>cheriſhes</hi> in it a ſpiritual Life, quickens Vertue, and makes us <hi>grow in Grace, and the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In ſhort, Zeal is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement Affection, or a ſtrong Byaſs and Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Soul towards its Object; and to be Zealouſly affected, is to be carried out with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Deſires and Endeavours after it; not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome Hatred, Trouble and Indignation at whatſoever does hinder or oppoſe it. This is the Nature of <hi>Zeal.</hi> But</p>
            <p>How muſt it be qualify'd, that it may be <hi>good</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49401:6"/>to be thus Zealouſly affected? Why, our Text mention two Qualifications to make it ſo.</p>
            <p>The one reſpects the <hi>Time</hi> of its continuance, it muſt be <hi>always;</hi> the other, the <hi>Object,</hi> it muſt be in a <hi>good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To be Zealouſly affected aright, it muſt be <hi>always,</hi> not <hi>now and then,</hi> by ſits and ſtarts; but keeping up an ardent flame of Love, ſtill burning in our Breaſts. The Apoſtle ſuppoſes here, that theſe <hi>Galatians</hi> were well enough affected whilſt he was <hi>preſent</hi> with them, but it did not continue in his <hi>abſence,</hi> it ſoon wore off, and therefore he wills them to be Zealouſly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>always.</hi> They who ſtill frequent and keep cloſe to the Worſhip and Communion of the Church, may be well enough ſuppos'd to be Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly affected towards it; but they who come to it only <hi>to ſerve a turn,</hi> may be juſtly thought otherwiſe; yea, when they who ſeldom or never attend the publick Worſhip, <hi>of a ſudden, on a particular occaſion,</hi> flock in great Numbers to it; and with that Formality and Appearance too, as if, with <hi>Jehu,</hi> they would alarm Spectators, to <hi>come and ſee their Zeal for the Lord of Hoſts:</hi> This is very ſuſpicious, and looks more like the reſult of <hi>Contrivance</hi> and <hi>Deſign,</hi> than the effect of <hi>true and ſound Religion.</hi> For true Zeal is <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent</hi> and <hi>laſting;</hi> it proceeds from a <hi>vital</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple within, which will maintain a kindly and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49401:7"/>conſtant heat in the Soul; 'tis not like the fits of an Ague, that come and go again, but like the <hi>Altar</hi> Fires, that were always kept burning, or the Veſtal Flames, that never went out: 'tis true indeed, it may, and does admit of <hi>intermiſſions,</hi> but 'tis never <hi>extinguiſh'd;</hi> but like the natural heat of the Heart, 'twill abide as long as Life continues. All that ſeeming Zeal of the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, that ſo often wears off, and grows <hi>cold</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, is but falſe Fire, 'tis only a <hi>painted,</hi> and no <hi>real</hi> Flame.</p>
            <p>If you obſerve it, you ſhall find ſome Men at <hi>ſome</hi> Times, and in <hi>ſome</hi> religious Exerciſes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding warm and zealous, their Affections ſeem all <hi>in a flame,</hi> and themſelves under the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports of Divine Love; who yet in a little time grow cold again, and have no appearance of Life or Heat left in them. Theſe are only <hi>paroxyſms</hi> of Zeal, and the <hi>preternatural heats</hi> of the Hypocrite's Devotion, whereas true Zeal is ever more <hi>uniform</hi> and <hi>laſting;</hi> and where the Spirit is truly <hi>touch'd with this Coal from the Altar,</hi> 'twill preſerve an habitual conſtant light and heat in the Soul. To this end, Zeal muſt be ſober and well temper'd, not over hot and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; for <hi>Nullum violentum eſt perpetuum,</hi> No violent thing is laſting: Such tranſports ſpend the Spirits too faſt, to continue long; Nature ſtruggles under any violence, and labours to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49401:7"/>eas'd and rid of it, and Religion too groans under ſuch violent <hi>fits</hi> of Zeal, and cannot long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſuch <hi>extreams;</hi> and therefore ſuch tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient fiery heats are far from the ſobriety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the temper of true Devotion. The Prophet reſembles ſome Men's Righteouſneſs to the <hi>Morning Cloud, and the early Dew that ſoon paſseth away;</hi> and we may liken others to a flaſh of Lightning, which gives a ſhort blaze, but is quickly out. The Apoſtle obſerves of ſome of theſe <hi>Galatians,</hi> that <hi>they ran well for a time</hi> in their Chriſtian Courſe; but they ſoon waxed faint and tired, and ſo loſt the Prize, for not holding out to the end of the Race. Chriſtianity is often in Scripture ſtyl'd a <hi>Warfare,</hi> in which, you know, 'tis not the furious <hi>Charge,</hi> but the deliberate <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Conſtancy</hi> that wins the Field: In like manner, 'tis <hi>Perſeverance</hi> only, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends our Zeal, and crowns our Actions with ſucceſs and victory. And therefore the Apoſtle wills us to <hi>hold on</hi> in our Chriſtian Courſe, and to be zealouſly affected <hi>always,</hi> even to the end; which is the firſt Qualification of true Zeal. The ſecond reſpects the <hi>Object</hi> about which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant, and that muſt be a <hi>good thing: It is good to be zealouſly affected always in a good thing;</hi> where we are taught to meaſure the <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of our Zeal, not by the <hi>height</hi> of the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of which 'tis compos'd; but by the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49401:8"/>the thing, about which 'tis employ'd. And here two things are to be obſerv'd for the better clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Matter: As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The object of our Zeal may be ſometimes a thing that is <hi>evil,</hi> and yet a Zeal about it may be a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>commendable</hi> thing; as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, All Sin in general, and particularly Atheiſm, Profaneneſs, Sacriledge, Schiſm, and the like, are all very <hi>bad</hi> things; and yet to be zealous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe, is to be Zealouſly affected in a <hi>good</hi> thing: but here the Zeal conſiſts, not in the <hi>love,</hi> but <hi>hatred</hi> of them, not in <hi>practiſing,</hi> but <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of them; yea, the <hi>worſe</hi> the thing is, the <hi>better</hi> is the <hi>Zeal</hi> that is employ'd againſt it: Thus the more bold and daring any Sin or Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is grown, the higher act of Zeal is it, to oppoſe and ſuppreſs it. Again,</p>
            <p>Secondly, A thing may be materially good, and yet a Zeal about it may be ſometimes a very bad thing; as for inſtance, All acts of Religion in general, and particularly Praying, Hearing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Manners, and the like, are all <hi>very good</hi> things; and yet a <hi>ſeeming</hi> Zeal about them, may be ſometimes a very evil and pernicious thing; as when they are embas'd by bad Ends, and made uſe of to promote evil Deſigns: you know the Phariſees <hi>made long Prayers, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to devour Widows houſes;</hi> you cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how ſome upon occaſion attend the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49401:8"/>Worſhip, only to <hi>qualify</hi> them for an <hi>Office,</hi> and take the holy Sacrament, to enable them to <hi>undermine</hi> the Communion of the Church. Do not ſome talk much of <hi>reforming</hi> the Manners of others, without any regard at all to their own? 'Tis no new thing to pretend <hi>Reformation,</hi> to carry on very bad Deſigns; and we all know what vile things have been acted under a <hi>cloak</hi> and colour of Religion: ſo that a great <hi>talk</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance</hi> for Reformation, may be rather Collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, than Zeal; and a pompous ſhew of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion about it, may be rather a mocking, than ſerving of GOD.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, A thing may be <hi>materially</hi> good, and carry a fair <hi>ſhew</hi> of being ſo; and yet may want many Qualifications, that are neceſſary to make it <hi>really</hi> and <hi>in truth</hi> ſuch. It may proceed from a bad <hi>Principle,</hi> be carried on by bad <hi>Means,</hi> and tend to a bad <hi>End;</hi> either of theſe may ſpoil the goodneſs of the thing, and marr the <hi>Zeal</hi> that is employ'd about it. The Object then of <hi>Zeal</hi> may be good and evil, and a hearty loving of the <hi>one,</hi> and hating the <hi>other,</hi> will juſtify our <hi>Zeal</hi> in <hi>both:</hi> for as Goodneſs hath charms enough to engage the Affections, ſo Sin hath deformity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beget diſlike and averſation; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to be zealous <hi>for</hi> the one, and <hi>againſt</hi> the other, is in both to be zealouſly affected in a good thing.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49401:9"/>
            <p>But to come to particulars: What are thoſe good or evil things, about which our Zeal may be thus <hi>lawfully</hi> and <hi>laudably</hi> employ'd? I ſhall mention ſome of the <hi>chief</hi> of them, the better to direct you in theſe great and weighty Matters of Religion. As,</p>
            <p>Firſt, To be zealous for the <hi>Glory of</hi> GOD, and the <hi>Honour of his Laws,</hi> is to be zealouſly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a good thing. The Glory of GOD is the great end of our Creation; and as the Almighty ever propounds it to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> ſo ought <hi>we</hi> to make it the principal aim and ſcope of all our Actions: <hi>Whether ye eat or drink</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>or whatever ye do, do all to the praiſe and glory of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. <hi>This</hi> is to be the chief care and buſineſs of our Lives, in which if we are ſincere, we cannot eaſily exceed; for the higheſt degrees of all <hi>pious</hi> Affections, are to be fix'd on GOD: He is to have our moſt ardent Love, our ſtrongeſt Deſire, our firmeſt Hope, our pureſt Joy; all which, when ſcrew'd up to the higheſt pitch, fall vaſtly ſhort of the infinite Perfections of his Nature, and our great Obligations to his Goodneſs. And therefore our Minds ſhould be eagerly bent on things, whereby GOD may be <hi>glorified,</hi> that his Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs may be celebrated in the World, and his Praiſes ſound to the ends of the Earth. Again, We are to ſet our ſelves with all our might and main a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49401:9"/>thoſe things, whereby GOD may be <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured,</hi> his Name <hi>prophan'd,</hi> his Worſhip <hi>neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> or <hi>contemn'd:</hi> we are to have a tender love and eſteem for GOD's <hi>Laws,</hi> and be deeply affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the breach and violation of them: Theſe are <hi>proper</hi> Matter for our <hi>Zeal,</hi> and are to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with the utmoſt warmth and vigour of all our Faculties; and when we ſtand thus affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Honour of GOD, and his Laws, then may we be truly ſaid to be <hi>zealouſly affected in a good thing;</hi> yea, in the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> good, and the <hi>beſt</hi> of things.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To be zealous for the <hi>Honour</hi> of CHRIST, and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> deliver'd by <hi>Him,</hi> is to be <hi>zealouſly affected in a good thing.</hi> This is the Zeal here recommended by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> namely, To ſtrive for the <hi>Truths</hi> of the Goſpel, againſt thoſe falſe Teachers, that would ſubvert or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine them. And herein, we of <hi>this Age</hi> ought to be more than ordinarily zealous, when the Being and Divinity of CHRIST are both call'd in queſtion, and the Myſteries of the Goſpel not only <hi>denied,</hi> but <hi>derided.</hi> Is not a <hi>Crucified</hi> Saviour once more become a <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> to ſome, and to others <hi>fooliſhneſs?</hi> And do not too many uſe their Tongues and Wits, in decrying all Divine Revelations? And is it not time to appear for Chriſt, and his Religion, in ſuch a profane and diſſolute Age? St. <hi>Jude</hi> exhorts
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49401:10"/>Chriſtians to <hi>Contend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> and elſewhere we are charg'd, not to let go, but to <hi>hold faſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Faith, without wavering;</hi> meaning, that we ſhould not <hi>betray</hi> it by Cowardiſe, nor <hi>corrupt</hi> it with Error, nor ſuffer it to be loſt or ſwallowed up by Infidelity; but to come forth in the defenſe of the Truth, againſt all its Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; to uſe our utmoſt endeavours, in our ſeveral Stations, to vindicate the Honour of our SAVIOUR, if ever we hope to be ſav'd by him: <hi>He that denies me before Men,</hi> (ſaith Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>him will I deny before my Father that is in Heaven.</hi> Now to <hi>diſown</hi> the <hi>Truths</hi> of the Goſpel, or to <hi>refuſe</hi> to <hi>appear</hi> in the defenſe of them, when call'd in queſtion, is indeed no better than to <hi>deny</hi> him: And what can ſuch expect, but to be for ever <hi>diſown'd</hi> and <hi>deny'd</hi> by him at the laſt day? Wherefore 'tis both the Duty and Intereſt of all that are called Chriſtians, to be zealous for the <hi>Honour of Chriſt,</hi> to vindicate his Truths, and to adorn his Doctrine with a holy Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To be zealous for the <hi>Church</hi> of GOD, is to be zealouſly affected in a <hi>good</hi> thing: And that as the Church is ſometimes taken for the <hi>Houſe</hi> of God, and likewiſe for the orderly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Divine <hi>Worſhip</hi> perform'd in it; both which are proper Matter to employ our Zeal.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49401:10"/>That ardent Love we owe to God, requires us to love the things of God, and to have a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to all that belongs to him; among which, we are commanded to <hi>hallow his Sabbath, and to reverence his Sanctuary. David</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Zeal of God's houſe had even conſumed him,</hi> Pſal. 69.9. He was ſo paſſionately affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>reverence</hi> and <hi>decency</hi> of thoſe Places, that he thought he could not better ſhew his Honour to God, than by reverencing the <hi>place</hi> where his Honour dwells. After that we read, what time, care and coſt King <hi>Solomon</hi> beſtow'd in building and beautifying the Temple; by which, he at once erected an Habitation for the Glory of his Maker, and a laſting Monument of his own Honour.</p>
            <p>But leſt any ſhould take this only for a piece of <hi>Old-Teſtament</hi> Zeal, we find our Bleſſed Saviour ſo zealous for the honour of the Temple, that he <hi>never</hi> diſcover'd a higher act of Indignation, than againſt the <hi>Prophaners</hi> of it; for himſelf whipp'd the Buyers and Sellers out of it, who had made the <hi>Houſe of Prayer a Den of Thieves,</hi> overturning the Tables of the Money-changers, and the Seats of them that ſold Doves; and that with an Indignation too, ſo much beſide his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary temper, that the Diſciples could not but call to mind, and apply to him, what was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of him, <hi>The Zeal of thy houſe hath eaten
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49401:11"/>me up.</hi> By this great example we learn, that a true Chriſtian Zeal may be <hi>well</hi> employ'd about the purifying of God's <hi>houſe,</hi> and ſecuring it from all profanation. Moreover, we find the Apoſtles extremely zealous for the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> of the Church, as alſo for the <hi>comelineſs, order</hi> and <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> of the <hi>publick</hi> Worſhip us'd in it: So that to be zealous againſt <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> which is the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting of God's holy Temple; and likewiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which is the dividing the Body of Chriſt, is a <hi>pious, well-grounded</hi> and <hi>commendable</hi> Zeal.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, To be zealous in the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and for the Honor of God's <hi>Miniſters,</hi> is to be zealouſly affected in a <hi>good</hi> thing; for theſe belong to him as his <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> and therefore are to be lov'd and treated accordingly: <hi>Let men ſo account of us</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the Myſteries of God,</hi> and for that reaſon to be counted <hi>worthy of double honor:</hi> The Kindneſs or Contempt ſhew'd to them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounds to <hi>him</hi> that ſends them; for <hi>He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>deſpiſes me, and he that deſpiſes me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me;</hi> and therefore our Zeal for Chriſt and his Truth, may and ought to be expreſt by eſpouſing the Cauſe of his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> eſpecially when the great Contempt of Religion hath occaſion'd too great a Contempt of the Diſpenſers of it.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49401:11"/>
            <p>Laſtly, To be zealous for the <hi>People</hi> of God, that is, for their Happineſs and Salvation, is to be zealouſly affected in a <hi>good</hi> thing: Next to the Glory of God, and our own Salvation, we are to tender the Welfare and Salvation of <hi>others;</hi> and this is to be done by our good Wiſhes, hearty Prayers, and beſt Endeavours for them: we find <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo far tranſported with love and deſire to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that he prefer'd their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Happineſs and Salvation, before the private welfare of his own Soul, praying thus in their behalf, either <hi>blot</hi> out their <hi>Sins,</hi> or <hi>blot</hi> out <hi>my name, out of the book that thou haſt written,</hi> Ex. 32.32. Under the like tranſport of Affection we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> declaring, that his <hi>Hearts deſire and Prayer unto God was, that Iſrael might be ſaved;</hi> withal wiſhing himſelf <hi>accurſed from Chriſt, for his Brethren and Kinsfolk according to the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 9.3. which great Examples re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to us, if not ſo high a pitch of <hi>Zeal,</hi> yet a moſt ardent love and deſire of doing good to all men; and eſpecially to uſe our beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to ſave their <hi>Souls,</hi> which is the greateſt good that we can do them; herein we ſhall tread in the ſteps of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> who <hi>went up and down doing good</hi> both to the Souls and Bodies of Men, which is ſuch a noble, generous and beneficial piece of Charity, as very well deſerves our utmoſt Zeal and Vigour.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49401:12"/>
            <p>In a word, To be zealous in the Cauſe of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, againſt Atheiſm and Profaneneſs; to be zealous for the Word of God, againſt Deiſm and Infidelity; for the Houſe and Worſhip of God, againſt Schiſm and Sacriledge; for the People of God, againſt Seducers that <hi>lay in wait to deceive,</hi> is to be zealouſly affected in <hi>good</hi> things, and is highly becoming all ſuch as are called by the Name of Chriſt, and would advance the Honour and Intereſt of Chriſtianity; which things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not only <hi>unwearied Diligence,</hi> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Reſolution</hi> to effect them; and therefore to engage and encourage you to ſet about them, I ſhall proceed to the</p>
            <p>Third thing to be conſider'd in our Text, <hi>viz.</hi> The goodneſs and excellency of <hi>true Zeal,</hi> from thoſe words, <hi>It is good to be zealouſly affected,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis <hi>good</hi> to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> for thereby we become like unto GOD, and imitate the Divine Goodneſs; 'tis <hi>good unto others,</hi> for as one Coal kindles another, ſo one man's Zeal helps to quicken another's, and blows up both into a bright and uſeful Flame: 'tis <hi>good</hi> to a <hi>whole</hi> Church and Country, who ſhare in the benefit, and reap the fruits of a well-guided Zeal; yea, 'tis <hi>good</hi> in all the fences of Goodneſs, for 'tis <hi>Bonum honeſtum, utile &amp; jucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> 'tis pious, profitable and pleaſant; 'tis the <hi>top</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> of all Vertue, the <hi>beauty, ſtrength</hi> and <hi>ornament</hi> of all Religion, and adds,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49401:12"/>as I may ſay, a Grace to all other Graces.</p>
            <p>Indeed, what Heat is to the Body, that is Zeal to the Soul; the very <hi>life, health</hi> and <hi>vigour</hi> of it, the ſource of all its activity and motion: and as the Body without Heat, is but a heavy, lumpiſh Carcaſe, ſo the Soul without Zeal, is ſluggiſh and unactive, and little better than <hi>dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins.</hi> But the Goodneſs of Zeal may be beſt ſeen in the <hi>good Effects</hi> produc'd by it, and the greatneſs of the Reward annext to it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, the Goodneſs of Zeal may be ſeen in the <hi>good Effects</hi> produc'd by it: Great and noble things have been atchiev'd by fervent Zeal; it hath inſpir'd the Soul with vigour and courage, ſtrong enough to conquer the greateſt difficulties, and to carry it above and beyond all oppoſition: by this <hi>Lot</hi> deferr'd the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and had there been a few more ſuch, it would have prevented that direful Conflagration that conſum'd them: For as one heat draws out an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo the fire of <hi>true Zeal</hi> weakens the fire of GOD's <hi>jealouſy,</hi> and keeps his <hi>wrath</hi> from breaking forth. <hi>Phinehas</hi>'s Zeal ſtopt the fury of the deſtroying Angel, caus'd the Plague to ceaſe, and reſtor'd Health and Peace unto <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The time would fail me, to rehearſe the many and great things that have been effected by it, for the honour of GOD, the welfare of his Church, and the ſafety of his People: neither indeed can it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49401:13"/>be otherwiſe, for <hi>Zeal</hi> kindles the flames of Love in the Breaſt of our Maker, and draws his Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to us; it engages him of our ſide, and <hi>if God be for us, who can be againſt us?</hi> Nothing can be too great for his infinite <hi>Goodneſs</hi> to grant, and nothing can be too hard for his infinite <hi>Power</hi> to effect for us.</p>
            <p>But the Goodneſs of <hi>Zeal</hi> will more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, in the <hi>greatneſs of the Reward</hi> annext to it hereafter; when our imperfect defires of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting <hi>God</hi>'s Glory now, will end in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of our own; when the little ſparks of Zeal here, will improve into a celeſtial Fire, which will ſtill burn in <hi>our</hi> Breaſts towards GOD, and in <hi>His</hi> towards <hi>us.</hi> In a word, This zealous diſpoſition will prepare and qualify us for the bliſsful Regions above, where our preſent faint Praiſings of GOD, ſhall be advanc'd into extaſy and rapture; and we, like the <hi>Seraphims,</hi> ſhall dwell for ever in the pure and unquenchable <hi>flames</hi> of Divine Love: Which, whoever well conſiders, will ſee abundant cauſe to ſay with the Apoſtle, that <hi>'Tis good to be Zealouſly affected al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in a good thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having ſhew'd the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Properties</hi> of <hi>true Zeal,</hi> the Paſſions of which 'tis compos'd, the things about which it is to be employ'd, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the goodneſs and excellency of it, when ſo qualify'd; I proceed now to conſider ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49401:13"/>of thoſe <hi>dangerous Miſtakes</hi> and <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of Zeal, that are to be found in the World; and theſe are indeed but too many, of which I ſhall mention a few: To which end you may obſerve,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That <hi>Zeal</hi> being compounded of the two <hi>ruling</hi> Paſſions of the Soul, <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Anger,</hi> may and often does admit of two <hi>extreams;</hi> the one in the <hi>exceſs,</hi> when 'tis over-hot and eager; the other in the <hi>defect,</hi> when 'tis too cold or lukewarm; and 'tis too frequent and eaſy for Men to fall into one of theſe: The firſt is an inordinate <hi>heat</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which tranſports Men beyond the true bounds, and runs it into ſpiritual <hi>Fury</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm;</hi> of this kind was that of the <hi>Jewiſh Zealots,</hi> who pretending to a ſecret Impulſe from above, did many vile and enormous things, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Riots, Rapins, Murders, and ſo deſtroy'd the Temple by an irregular Zeal in defending it; which intemperate heat of theirs, occaſion'd great Troubles to that whole Church and Nation. And very like to this is the <hi>furious</hi> and <hi>diſorderly</hi> Zeal of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> in our days, who under a pretence of higher Illuminations, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpirations, have greatly diſturb'd the peace of Kingdoms, and by their fierce and eager Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions about Religion, have endanger'd the loſs of all: This hot <hi>fiery</hi> Zeal our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our blam'd in ſome of his own Diſciples, who, in a fit of Rage, call'd for Fire from Heaven,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49401:14"/>to conſume the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> for which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that ſharp Rebuke, that <hi>They knew not what manner of Spirit they were of;</hi> they did not know or conſider the true Spirit of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which was not to <hi>deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> So that a Zeal that is void of Charity, and inſenſible of the Publick Good, is certainly irregular; and when it tranſports Men beyond the bounds of Meekneſs and Sobriety, is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with true Religion: and therefore to ſet it right, it muſt be temper'd with Wiſdom, and abound more in the <hi>mild</hi> and <hi>good-natur'd Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> than in the more <hi>vehement</hi> and <hi>wrathful Paſſions,</hi> which are too apt to become inordinate: And theſe extravagant heats and tranſports in Matters of Religion, are the exceſs of <hi>Zeal,</hi> the miſchief whereof is too viſible to need laying open.</p>
            <p>But 'twere well, if ſome Men did not offend as much in the <hi>defect,</hi> as others do in the <hi>exceſs</hi> of <hi>Zeal;</hi> and that the evil of the <hi>one,</hi> were not as dangerous as the miſchief of the <hi>other:</hi> But alas! the miſeries of <hi>both</hi> are too apparent to be either deny'd or diſguis'd: For is not ſome Men's indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and careleſsneſs in Religion, as much ſhort of <hi>true Zeal,</hi> as others fierce paſſions and contentions are beyond it? And is not <hi>one</hi> of theſe too often the cauſe or occaſion of the <hi>other?</hi> Does not Religion ſuffer as much in the Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and want of Sobriety in <hi>ſome</hi> Men's Lives,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49401:14"/>as by the inordinate <hi>Zeal,</hi> and unneceſſary Rigours of <hi>others?</hi> And is not Atheiſm the plain conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of the open looſeneſs of the one, as well as the falſe and pretended ſtrictneſs of the other? Of both theſe <hi>our</hi> unhappy Age affords but too many Inſtances, which may teach us to avoid both theſe Rocks, and to ſteer our Courſe between the fury of ſome Men's <hi>Zeal,</hi> and the ſcandal of others Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another Error in <hi>Zeal,</hi> is when 'tis void of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> or acts contrary to it: this is a <hi>blind Zeal,</hi> which leads Men headlong into many extravagancies; and this is in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure owing either to the <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>ſubtlety</hi> of falſe Teachers, who ſeek to work on the <hi>Paſſions</hi> of Men, without rightly informing their <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> by which means they are taught eagerly to contend for, or againſt things, without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the goodneſs or badneſs of either. If you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, you ſhall find thoſe many times the greateſt <hi>Zealots,</hi> that are moſt ignorant; like the <hi>Andabatae</hi> fighting in the dark, and contending for they know not what, or why. St. <hi>Paul</hi> bore Record of ſome in his time, that they had a <hi>Zeal,</hi> but 'twas <hi>not according to knowledge:</hi> This is a Heat without Light, which tends rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, than to direct; true <hi>Zeal</hi> in the <hi>Heart</hi> is evermore guided by a true light in the <hi>Head,</hi> it begins with Knowledge, and is conducted by it;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49401:15"/>whereas falſe <hi>Zeal</hi> begins with the Affections, and commonly ends there, ſeldom going any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than an ignorant and violent Paſſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is a <hi>counterfeit</hi> and <hi>hypocritical Zeal,</hi> which warms only the <hi>out-ſide,</hi> and conſiſts in a ſuperficial ſhew of Piety and Devotion; it reſembles the heat of a Feaver, that ſcorches the extreme parts, but leaves the Heart cold and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected: <hi>Pone in pectore dextram, nil calet:</hi> There is no heat or warmth at all within, even when it ſeems to burn and flame moſt without. Of this kind was the Zeal of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who <hi>faſted</hi> and <hi>prayed, to be ſeen of men,</hi> and did all their good Works meerly for Vanity and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; they had no <hi>inward</hi> Principle of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Life or Motion, but were acted meerly by external Motives and Inducements: ſuch are the ſuperficial heats of too many <hi>Zealots,</hi> who ſeem all on fire without, when the Heart, like <hi>Nabal</hi>'s, is as cold as a Stone.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, There is a Temporary <hi>Zeal,</hi> which like a Vapour or Comet, <hi>appeareth for a while, and then vaniſheth away:</hi> ſuch was that of <hi>Jehu,</hi> who <hi>drove on</hi> furiouſly for a time, and deſtroy'd the Monuments of Idolatry; but being ſettled in the Kingdom, his <hi>Zeal</hi> for Religion was at end, and turn'd only to his own advancement. Such likewiſe was the Mercenary and Selfiſh <hi>Zeal</hi> of thoſe, that followed our bleſſed Saviour <hi>for the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49401:15"/>Loaves,</hi> and kept with him while any thing was to be gotten by him; but when that fail'd, they forſook and walked no more with him: This is a Flame that is blown in and out with the Wind, and varies with every blaſt. Again,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, There is a <hi>partial Zeal,</hi> which makes Men warm in <hi>ſome</hi> Duties of Religion, and cold in others of equal neceſſity and importance; and likewiſe very earneſt in ſuppreſſing <hi>one or more</hi> Vices, and yet very favourable and indulgent to <hi>others</hi> equally crying and enormous. If you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, you will find ſome hot enough for <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but cold for <hi>Praying;</hi> and tho' they talk much of reforming of <hi>others</hi> Manners, are yet but too careleſs and negligent of <hi>their own.</hi> May we not ſee many great Enemies indeed to Idolatry and Profaneneſs, who yet are well enough recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to Sacriledge and Schiſm? and make up that with advantage to one Vice, which they ſeem to take from another. This is to <hi>compound</hi> the Matter with GOD, and to make the keeping of one Law, atone for the breach of another. True and thorough Reformation extends to the hatred of <hi>all</hi> Vice, and the practice of <hi>all</hi> Vertue; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, the moſt zealous pretences to <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> are but falſhood and hypocriſy.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, There is a <hi>buſy pragmatical</hi> Zeal, that carries private Men beyond the bounds of <hi>their own</hi> Calling and Buſineſs, and makes them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49401:16"/>the Callings and Buſineſs of others, intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the Offices of Princes, Magiſtrates, Judges and Miniſters; prying into and cenſuring the Actions of their Superiors, and dictating to thoſe by whom they are to be govern'd: Theſe are thoſe <hi>buſy-bodies</hi> mention'd by the Apoſtle, who meddle with things they underſtand not, and belong not to them: True Zeal makes Men ſtudy <hi>to be quiet, and do their own buſineſs,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thruſting themſelves unſeaſonably into other Men's; it puts Men upon the ſtudy of <hi>their own</hi> Hearts, mortifying <hi>their own</hi> Sins, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>their own</hi> Lives, which is enough to employ the Zeal of the Beſt Chriſtian: whereas 'tis too apparent, how ſome Men's Zeal prompts them to wander too much abroad, and to converſe too little at home; hence you ſhall find them very fierce and forward in declaiming againſt the Sins of others, as if they had <hi>none</hi> of their own to amend or complain of; how frequently do they call to Heaven for Vengeance on <hi>National</hi> Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, as if they had no <hi>ſhare</hi> in the Guilt, and were ſecur'd from bearing a <hi>part</hi> in the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it? Yea, 'tis no new thing for them, to condemn that in others, which they allow in themſelves; and to inveigh bitterly againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers failings, when at the ſame time they eaſily overlook their own enormities: This is the guiſe and practice of too many Zealots, which may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49401:16"/>carry ſomething of the ſhew, but hath nothing of the ſubſtance and reality of True Religion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Zeal</hi> commended in our Text, hath reſpect to <hi>Things,</hi> not Perſons: 'tis good to be zealouſly affected always in a good <hi>Thing:</hi> A Zeal either for, or againſt <hi>Perſons</hi> is commonly <hi>factious</hi> and <hi>diſorderly:</hi> The <hi>having ſome Men's Perſons in Admiration,</hi> and others in Contempt, hath occaſion'd moſt of the Schiſms and Diviſions in the Chriſtian Church: This was the great fault of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who by crying up one Teacher, to the decrying of another, fell into ſundry Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Factions, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked in them, tho' their Zeal ran mightily to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>himſelf;</hi> for finding they had made <hi>him</hi> the Head of a Party, he ſeverely check'd their partiality, and the more they ſought to magnify <hi>him,</hi> the more he endeavour'd to leſſen <hi>himſelf: Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is Paul? and who is Apollo? Who?</hi> (ſaith an eminent Father on thoſe Words) <hi>why, they were ſome of the chief Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt: And yet we find St.</hi> Paul <hi>not only ſtile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf the leaſt of the Apoſtles, but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Sinners, to keep men from having too high thoughts and admiration of him.</hi> And if it were ſtrife and envying to ſet up for <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Cephas;</hi> certainly it can be no true Zeal to ſet up for far inferior Perſons.</p>
            <p>This is a Matter worthy the conſideration of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49401:17"/>all ſuch as have Men's <hi>Perſons</hi> in admiration, running after different Teachers, to the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the Church, which is the great miſery and malady of <hi>our</hi> unhappy Age.</p>
            <p>And now for the application of this Diſcourſe; tho' many uſeful Leſſons might be infer'd from it, yet I ſhall confine my ſelf to <hi>two,</hi> which very naturally and eaſily flow from it. For,</p>
            <p>If it be good to be Zealouſly affected in a good thing, then 1ſt. It muſt be <hi>bad</hi> to be Zealouſly affected in an <hi>ill</hi> thing; and 2ly, It can be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be <hi>lukewarm</hi> and <hi>coldly affected</hi> in a <hi>good</hi> thing: Of both which, that I may not treſpaſs too much upon your patience, I ſhall ſpeak very briefly. And,</p>
            <p>1ſt. We may learn from hence, that 'tis <hi>bad</hi> to be Zealouſly affected in an <hi>ill</hi> thing: 'Tis a double fault, firſt to eſpouſe a bad Cauſe, and then to be warm and zealous in promoting it; he that is out of the way, the faſter he goes, the farther he goes out of it; and to ſet him right, he muſt go it back again, and mend his pace after: To rectify a bad Zeal, we muſt alter and unravel our former Courſe, and labour to <hi>undo</hi> all that we have done amiſs. True <hi>Zeal</hi> is always <hi>againſt,</hi> and never <hi>for</hi> an <hi>evil</hi> thing; and therefore to be zealous for a <hi>Party,</hi> and hot in promoting <hi>Faction</hi> or <hi>Diviſion,</hi> is to employ it in a very <hi>bad</hi> thing: To favour a <hi>wrong</hi> Cauſe, or diſcountenance a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49401:17"/>
               <hi>good</hi> one, are <hi>both</hi> equally abominable; and he that is warm in <hi>either,</hi> is clearly out of the way, and can never <hi>judge righteous Judgment:</hi> to ſpend our Zeal in encouraging of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and promote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>diſorder</hi> and <hi>diſturbance</hi> in the World, is to put one of the <hi>beſt things</hi> to one of the <hi>worſt uſes;</hi> and therefore we find Zeal commonly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to Fire, than which as no Element is more uſeful and reviving, whilſt it remains on the Hearth, and keeps within its due place and bounds, ſo none is more pernicious and deſtructive, when once refuſing confinement, it breaks forth and invades the Houſe-top: For the ſame reaſon 'tis ſometimes compar'd to the natural heat of the Body, which in its due temper and moderation, is the ſpring both of Life and Health, and the ſource of all vital Operations; but when it grows into exceſs, and breaks out into burning Feavers, it inflames the Spirits, and <hi>ſets on fire the whole Courſe of Nature:</hi> Juſt ſo is it with Zeal, which, if duly plac'd and regulated, is the ſupport and ornament of the Soul, fills it with a lively and vigorous Heat, and fits it for brave and noble Undertakings; but when 'tis miſplac'd, or runs into exceſs, 'tis no better than Wild-fire, and ſets whole Countries into a combuſtion; which ſhews what great care is to be taken, that it be guided with Knowledge, and plac'd upon right Objects, ſuch as may be not only <hi>materially,</hi> but in <hi>all</hi> its</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49401:18"/>
            <p>It being equally evil, to be zealous in a <hi>bad</hi> Cauſe, and lukewarm in a <hi>good,</hi> let us endeavour to avoid both extreams; and learn ſo to regulate and fix our Zeal, that it may be ſtill placed on right Objects, kept within its due bounds, and directed to good ends: So ſhall this Sacred fire improve into a Celeſtial flame, that will be ſtill burning in our Breaſts towards God, and for ever derive upon us the bleſſed Influences of Divine Love: Which God grant for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honor, Might, Majeſty and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, both now and for evermore.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
